原视频名：NASA Will Spend $2,941,394,557 On SpaceX's Massive Lunar Starship Lander!!!
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/GuSM_-Aw5HM
原视频发布日期：20210417
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
And yesterday the world was taken by surprise
昨天 整个世界都震惊了
when SpaceX won NASA's Human Landing System award
在SpaceX获得NASA的载人着陆系统合同的时候
which frankly is seems kind of ridiculous
实话说 这有点滑稽
especially when you put all three competitors next to each other
特别是当你把这三个竞争对手放在一起的时候
and you realize that SpaceX's Starship towers like a monolith over the other options.
你就会意识到SpaceX的Starship就像一块巨石一样耸立在其他选项之上
We always thought it was a long shot to have this in there
我们一直认为 要想把它放在那里 是很难的事情
and it might be taken as an insurance option
而且(只是)可以作为一种保险的选择
but it's the only option that NASA has chosen.
但这是NASA作出的唯一选择
They're going to get 2.9 billion dollars over the next few years
他们将在未来几年内获得29亿美元的资金
and this is to test, develop, demonstrate the vehicle.
而这是为了测试 开发 验证航天器
Now it's not going to cover long-term lunar landing. That's coming later.
那么 合同不会涵盖长期的月球着陆 那是以后的事
but they will in theory be the people
但理论上 SpaceX将会
to carry the first humans from the US back to the moon at some point in the next decade.
在未来十年的某个时间点 将第一批美国人运回月球
So yeah look this caught us by surprise because of the choice
那么 是的 这个选择让我们感到惊讶
but it also caused by surprise because it was suddenly sort of leaked at the last minute
但同样是意想不到的 因为这差不多是在最后时刻才泄漏出来
and I think what happened was on Friday morning
而我想事情的发生是在周五早上
there were news stories starting to appear that SpaceX had won
有新闻报道开始说 SpaceX已经赢得了合同
and then Washington Post suddenly had a copy of NASA's internal document with all the details
然后华盛顿邮报突然得到了一份NASA的内部文件的副本 包含了有所有的细节
and suddenly NASA says oh we're gonna have a press conference at 4 pm on a Friday
然后突然间 NASA说 哦 我们会在周五下午4点开一个新闻发布会
who has a press conference at 4 pm on Friday.
接着确实在周五下午4点开了新闻发布会
Someone that's really trying to address something before the weekend.
有人真的是要赶在周末前解决一些问题啊
So yeah they have this. It was nicely produced.
那么是的 NASA放出了这个做得不错的视频
I think it was probably coming maybe next week but yeah SpaceX won it.
我认为可能是下周才会放出消息 但是没错 SpaceX赢了
(电话)新闻发布会视频 NASA. Human Landing System Announcement Media Teleconference
youtu.be/y6BqZrs0x4E
There was nobody from SpaceX answering questions at this press conference
在新闻发布会上 没有SpaceX的人来回答问题
which led to some interesting problems
这导致了一些有趣的问题
where people would have very good questions for SpaceX
也就是人们(本)会有非常好的问题向SpaceX提出
and they said ask SpaceX. Oh they're not here.
而他们说去问SpaceX吧 哦 他们不在这里
I mean to be fair some of the questions were things like how does Starship integrate with SLS
我是指 公平地讲 有些类似Starship如何与SLS整合的问题
and that's a question best answered using Kerbal Space Program rather than actual science.
像这种问题更适合用坎巴拉太空计划而不是实际的科学来回答
The source selection statement also showed that
原始的选择声明还显示
the national team consisting of Blue Origin, Lockheed Martin, Northrop Grumman and Draper.
由蓝色起源 洛克希德·马丁 诺斯罗普·格鲁曼和德雷珀组成的国家队
They would have been the second choice
他们本来是第二选择
and the Dynetics lander which I liked for many reasons
还有各方面我都喜欢的Dynetics着陆器
that would have been the third choice.
本来是第三选择
But these were all largely driven by cost.
但这些主要都是由费用驱动的
The cost was the biggest problem.
费用是最大的问题
If you remember the previous administration had basically asked for something like
如果你还记得上届政府基本上要求了这些东西 比如
three billion dollars to fund the Human Landing System development program
要求用30亿美元资助载人着陆系统开发项目
and congress was like well we can't steer this money to our district
而国会是这样的 好吧 我们不能引导这些钱到我们的地区(选区)
根据spacenews.com/nasa-receives-23-271-billion-in-fiscal-year-2021-omnibus-spending-bill/，
是8.5亿美元(2021年NASA预算)
so we're just going to give you a billion dollars.
那么 我们只给你10亿美元
It wasn't even that.
甚至都没达到
It might have been less.
可能已经更少
But within that lower budget
但在这个较低的预算范围内
none of the options that had been submitted were actually could be funded at that level
所提交的备选方案实际上都不能按这一水平来提供资金
so NASA worked with the various bidders
所以NASA与投标人合作
and got SpaceX to not change the amount of money they were asking for
并得以让SpaceX不改变他们要求的费用
but to adjust the timeline so the first year could fit within the money that they had available
但去调整时间表 以让第一年的研发能在他们现有的资金范围内完成
and SpaceX were the only one that were even remotely in the ballpark
而SpaceX提供的方案是唯一的那个资金(本就比较低且)方便调整的
so they are pretty much the winners
所以他们差不多就是赢家了
and this is not going to make many people in congress happy.
而这是不会让国会中的很多人高兴的
I mean like it's an open competition and there's lobbyists from various groups
我是指 这是一个公开的竞争 存在着来自不同组织的说客
but I don't think SpaceX have quite the same draw as your Lockheed Martin, Northrop Grumman, Blue Origin etc.
但我觉得SpaceX的吸引力还不如洛克希德·马丁 诺斯罗普·格鲁曼 蓝色起源等
There's already been at least one complaint
已经有至少一个埋怨
其实是国会众议院管辖NASA的科学，航天和技术委员会 主席
艾迪·伯尼斯·強森(Eddie Bernice Johnson)
by I think was chairman or chairwoman of some committee that it works on spending.
我想是来自一些从事财政支出相关的委员会的女主席
Basically saying why are you making this critical decision on the Human Landing System
基本上是在说 你为什么要在载人着陆系统上做出这个关键的决定
before we have approved the new NASA administrator and deputy administrator.
在我们批准新的NASA局长和副局长之前
And also by the way lost in the news yesterday was that
还有顺便说一下在昨天的新闻中被忽略的是
the official nomination for Pamela Melroy as deputy administrator came out
NASA副局长的提名出来了 是Pamela Melroy
so I'm excited for her because she is a legitimate awesome astronaut space person.
那么 我为她感到兴奋 因为她是一个真正的优秀的宇航员
Hopefully will do great things for NASA.
希望她能为NASA做出杰出的贡献
But yeah it's entirely possible that there will be appeals
但是 是的 完全可能发生上诉
and there might be some political rummaging
可能会有一些政治上的检查
but I'm hoping this doesn't mean so much that SpaceX has a chance of losing this.
但我希望这并不意味着SpaceX会失去这个项目
So much that we have a chance to get the funding you would need for a second option
并不意味着 会有足够的资金去实现第二个选择
because I think dissimilar redundancy is something that is very important when you're trying to do things fast.
因为我认为在你想要快速完成什么东西的时候 非相似余度是非常重要的
And I will say by the way that the Human Landing System submission process.
而且顺便我想说一下 载人着陆系统的提交程序
They were targeting the 2024 landing date.
他们的目标着陆时间是2024年
That is clearly not going to happen.
而这显然是不会发生的
So there is a lot more leeway a lot more wiggle room in this
那么 着陆时间方面会有更多的回旋余地
than is otherwise suggested by this source selection.
会比这个原本的竞标来得更多
So anyway let's go back and look at the competitors remember.
那么不管怎么说 我们还是回过头来看看这些竞争者 还记得吗
So yeah when it was announced or when the the finalists were showing off
那么 是的 在结果宣布的时候 或者说决赛选手们公布的时候
everybody thought that the national team had probably the strongest bid
每个人都认为国家队可能是最强的竞标者
because it looked closest to what NASA wanted
因为它看起来最接近NASA的要求
so the national team, Blue Origin, Lockheed Martin, Northrop Grumman it was a three-stage lander.
那么国家队 蓝色起源 洛克希德·马丁 诺斯罗普·格鲁曼 这个方案是个三级的着陆器
You had the ascent stage which had the humans cabin in it where the people would fly.
上升级里面有载人的舱室 飞行的时候人们呆在里面
There was a descent stage that would carry that to the moon
还有一个下降级 可以把它带到月球上
and then there was a tug like an orbital element
然后还有一个像轨道拖船一样的轨道级
which would carry this stack from the halo orbit at the gateway down to low lunar orbit
会把这个组合体从轨道门户的晕轮轨道运到低月球轨道
and then stay in orbit and then when the ascent element returned
然后停留在轨道上 直到上升级返回时
it would carry the ascent element back to the gateway again.
它会携带上升级再次回到门户空间站
So this in many ways matched what NASA was looking for
那么这在很多方面都符合NASA的要求
but it didn't win because it turns out that it was very expensive and there were technical issues.
但它没有赢 因为事实证明 它是非常昂贵的 而且有技术问题
Dynetics they had a radical idea which I really liked
Dynetics他们有一个激进的想法 我非常喜欢
because instead of building this thing as a vertical stack they sort of built it sideways
因为他们没有把这个组合体竖着造 而是横着造
where you had this cabin in the middle which would pretty much set all right on the moon.
这样 驾驶舱就可以放中间 (这样着陆后 驾驶舱就)差不多就完全在月球上了
So you could actually step out of the airlock and down a couple of steps onto the moon
那么实际上你可以走出气闸 (只需)走下几级台阶就能到月球上
rather than descending this really huge ladder on the side of the national team.
而不是从国家队着陆器侧面这个非常巨大的梯子上下来
The national team's lander was 14 meters tall.
国家队的着陆器有14米高
And to be fair Dynetics lander was that tall if you included the solar panels that stuck upwards.
而且公平地说 Dynetics的着陆器也有这么高 如果你算上向上伸出的太阳能电池板
But yeah the rocket engines would be on the side
但是 是的 火箭发动机会在侧面
and then they would have drop tanks that would be dropped during the descent towards the moon.
然后他们会在向月球下降的过程中扔下储罐
And anyway and then we finally come to Starship.
总之 最后我们来到了Starship
We all know what Starship looks like it's big in stainless steel with wings.
我们都知道Starship是什么样子的 它很大 是不锈钢的 有翼面
This is a slightly different version which has it's painted white.
而月球版Starship是一个略有不同的版本 它被涂成了白色
It has a ring of solar panels a black section around.
它有一圈太阳能电池板 也就是那一圈黑色的部分
It has none of the fins because there's no air on the moon
因为月球上没有空气 所以它没有翼面
and you have to actually use rocket engines to slow down
而你必须真的去用火箭发动机来减速
but for final landing it had a ring of angled engines about halfway up the rocket
但为了最后的着陆 大约在火箭的一半处 有一圈倾斜的发动机
and we're not clear what those engines are
而我们也不清楚这些发动机是什么
but the new render shows that there's something like 25 of them.
但新的渲染图显示 有约25台这样的发动机
So that's far too many for them to be super dracos
那么他们的数量可太多了 不可能是超级天龙座
so this would probably have to be some sort of new thruster
所以 这可能必须得是某种新的推进器
2021年的渲染图
that uses methane and liquid oxygen hopefully.
希望是使用甲烷和液态氧的
Yeah I mean there's other things that are changed in the new Starship render.
是的 我是指 还有其他的东西 在新的Starship渲染图里改变了
Now that we've got the winners out there.
现在我们已经有了赢家了
The legs have been expanded
腿已经扩大了
because the landing legs that are currently on the test vehicles.
因为目前测试版航天器上的着陆腿
Obviously those are small and temporary
显然都偏小而且是临时性质的
but even when they get towards a production leg design
但即使他们去设计量产版的着陆腿时
they're still going to have to fit within a sort of narrow envelope
他们仍将不得不把它容纳在一个狭窄的外壳内
so that they can be they can be screened from the aerodynamic effects.
这样他们就可以让它免受空气动力效应的影响
Whereas for the moon they can just have big legs that fall down provide a wider base.
而对于月球来说 放下大的着陆腿 这样底部就更宽
So these have at least four legs. It's kind of hard to tell the geometry doesn't look quite right.
那么渲染图上的Starship至少有四条腿 这很难看出 因为这里的几何结构看着不太对
With big landing pads like two three meter wide landing pads.
有了像这样2-3米宽的着陆垫
Well I think these things once they're deployed
我想这些东西一旦部署好了
they might stay deployed with some sort of shock absorber.
可能也会带有某种减震器
And there's a new solar panels on there and new landing thruster designs.
而上面还有新的太阳能电池板和新的着陆推进器设计
But there's also some changes to the nose
但鼻锥也有一些变化
because obviously it's going to have to be docking to other spacecraft.
因为很明显 它必须与其他航天器对接
So the selection statement it looked hard at all of these proposals.
那么在选择声明中 NASA认真地研究了所有这些提案
I mean of course we're looking at Starship
我是指 当然 我们正在研究Starship
and many people are trying to criticize it for their various problems or whatever
而很多人都想批评它的各种问题什么的
but you're to be fair all the teams have built hardware for this proposal.
但公平地说 所有的团队都已经为这个提案制造了设备
Blue Origin and Dynetics, they both have these fantastic mock-ups
蓝色起源和Dynetics都制造了很棒的模型
showing high-fidelity human factors part of the lander.
高度精确地展示了着陆器的载人段
So you can get in and look inside them.
那么你可以进去看看他们的内部
SpaceX have built a lot of well flying things that have become scrap things
SpaceX制造了很多飞行性能良好的东西 但这些东西都已经成了废品
but building stuff that actually flies put them ahead of the curve quite significantly
但制造真正能飞的东西却让他们领先了很多
even if they haven't failed to demonstrate a proper complete landing cycle.
即使他们还没能验证一个完整且适当的着陆周期
But what NASA saw when they looked at Starship was
但当NASA看到Starship的时候 他们看到的是
they saw a vehicle that wasn't breaking the laws of physics in any way.
一个符合物理定律的航天器
It did it required lots of R&D but so did the other competitors
它确实需要大量的研发 但其他竞争对手也是如此
and it was just so much larger.
而且它确实大一截儿
It had two air locks with independent life support systems
它有两个配有独立的生命支持系统的气闸
which really expand your survivability envelope.
这真的扩展了你的生存能力范围
Also it had a lot of room for expansion.
同时它也有很大的扩展空间
And while this wasn't part of this proposal
同时 虽然这不是这个提案中的一部分
the teams were required to come up with proposals for how they would extend their lander
各个团队还被要求就如何扩展其着陆器提出计划
and turn it into a more sustainable system.
并把它变成一个更可持续的系统
And SpaceX had lots of space to expand and lots of margin everywhere.
而SpaceX有很多的空间可以扩展 到处都有很多的余地
Dynetics actually came into the competition with their proposal when it was analyzed by NASA,
Dynetics参与竞争的方案 被NASA分析发现
they found that they had negative mass.
有负质量
They were carrying negative mass margin.
他们的质量冗余为负
No no I mean like you think negative mass oh that's cool it floats upward.
不 不 我是指 这不是像你认为的那样 负质量哦 这很酷 它可以向上漂浮
No no negative mass margin is bad.
不 不 负质量冗余是不好的
It means your design is heavier than it should be
这意味着你的设计比它应该的重
and you have to somehow cut mass from it
而你必须以某种方式把它的质量削减
rather than having room to grow when you're encountering problems that was like a big negative.
而不是当你遇到问题需要冗余度时(还可以增加质量) 这就像一个很大的负面问题
It was a big part of why Dynetics rating went from being acceptable to being marginal.
这也是Dynetics的评级从可接受变成勉强的一个重要原因
All the teams had various technologies that were identified as having low technological readiness levels.
所有的团队都有各种被认定为准备度低的技术
The propulsion systems for the national team in particular
尤其是国家队的推进系统
there were multiple propulsion systems none of which had been really properly developed at this time.
其中有多个推进系统都没有在评估时被真正地开发出来
SpaceX at least of course have their Raptors and those are actually flying
SpaceX至少有他们的猛禽 而且这些猛禽实际上是飞过了
RUD = Rapid Unscheduled Disassembly，快速意外解体
even if they are sometimes involved in giant RUDs.
即使有时会牵涉到巨大的RUD
And incidentally the SN15 we're now starting to see the new generation of Raptors coming down to Boca Chica.
而顺带一提的是SN15 我们现在开始看到新一代的猛禽来到了博卡奇卡
And there's a number of changes to this design.
而且这个设计有很多变化
They're not radical.
这些变化并不剧烈
But if you look you can see your pipe layouts change. Some of the manifold designs have been recast.
但如果你仔细看 你会发现管道布局的变化 一些歧管的设计已经改变
So hoping that that will improve their reliability.
所以希望这能提高猛禽的可靠性
Now the national team by the way it was noticed that they also had a non-compliant bid
那么顺便说下国家队 NASA也注意到了他们也有一个不符合要求的投标书
which basically said part of the requirements was that
其中基本上是说 部分要求是
the bids had to not have any advance payments for work that would be done in the future.
投标书必须没有任何预付款用于未来进行的工作
They had to be structured in such a way that they weren't getting a lot of money upfront
他们的结构必须是这样的方式 这样他们就得不到很多预付款
and yeah the national team had this by accident supposedly
那么是的 国家队的投标书应该是意外地添加了这一部分
and NASA would have had to negotiate with them to fix this to make it compliant.
而NASA将不得不与他们协商 来修复这一点 使其符合要求
Yeah it's one of these things you only discover when you really start looking hard at things.
是的 这种事情 只有在你真正开始研究的时候才会发现
The one of the concerns with SpaceX was the fact that refueling this thing
而其中一个NASA对SpaceX担心的问题是 推进剂在轨加注
is going to take like half a dozen flights to get the tanker filled up in orbit.
要花差不多六七次飞行才能让储罐版航天器在轨道上加满推进剂
But sort of the upside of that was that all this refueling stuff needed to happen in low earth orbit.
但这种做法的好处是 所有这些燃料补加的事情都(只)需要在近地轨道上进行
And that actually it worked well for them
而实际上这对他们来说很好
so they could load up the tanker and if there were problems they would have time to adjust their schedule.
这样他们就可以把储罐版航天器的燃料加满 而如果有问题 还有时间调整计划
It was a relatively easy target.
这是一个比较容易的目标
Whereas the other landers all required refueling
而其他的着陆器都需要补充燃料
but their design had the lander sent out to the moon
但他们的设计是将着陆器送到月球
and then in lunar orbit they would be assembled and refueled.
然后在月球轨道上进行组装和推进剂补加
And that was of course that needed fewer launches.
当然这样(只)需较少的发射次数
But it wasn't in low earth orbit so that counted.
但发射的目标轨道不是近地轨道 那么这也比较困难
There was a bit of a wash either way.
无论哪种方式都有一点互有得失的意味
All of these things are fairly complex
所有这些事情都相当复杂
compared to building a ginormous Saturn V and putting all your stuff onto a single launch.
相比于建造一个巨大的土星五号 并把所有的东西放在一次发射上
Yeah the biggest factor ultimately is that SpaceX
是啊 最大的因素最终是SpaceX
bizarrely despite having this monster lander were the cheapest.
奇怪的是 尽管这个怪物着陆器是最便宜的
And that's all they could afford to do.
但这也是他们所能承受的一切
And a lot of this is down to SpaceX already developing it with their own money and with other investors
而这很大程度上归功于SpaceX已经用自己和其他投资者的钱一起开发了它
很多年前人们会问我Starship没有商业价值 你将如何支付它的费用 那么我的回答是月球任务
because they have specific tasks in mind not just for Starship but for Super Heavy in general
因为总体上他们不仅对Starship 而且对Super Heavy都有特定的任务要求
and that counts for a lot.
而这也算得上是一个很大的问题
It may be reaching high.
这也许会满足很高的目标
It may be pushing thing at the limits.
也许这很难做到 非常极限
But that's ultimately how this works.
但根本上 Starship方案就是这样
And you of course this then says well what does that mean for the rest of Artemis
而你当然会问 这对阿尔忒弥斯的其他部分来说意味着什么？
because this is so much bigger than anything else there.
因为这比这个计划中的其他东西都要大得多
If you dock all the parts of the gateway together.
如果你把所有门户空间站的部分对接在一起
Starship is still going to be bigger than all of that.
Starship还是会比整个门户空间站都要大
It's going to look a bit ridiculous at some point.
在某些时候 它会显得有点可笑
And maybe this just represents a sort of inflection point
而也许这只是一个转折点而已
where NASA is now seeing the wisdom of Starship through all the various programs
就在这时 NASA通过各种计划看到了Starship的智慧
and does want to get involved because they see it as a viable way forwards.
并确实想参与其中 因为他们认为这是一条可行的前进道路
Of course things could go wrong.
当然 事情可能会出错
We've got several years before this is fully developed.
还有几年的时间Starship才会开发完毕
But it's entirely possible.
但这是完全有可能的
We look back and we see this moment as being a critical moment in development of human spaceflight going forwards
(有朝一日) 我们回过头来看 会认为此刻是载人航天飞行开发的关键时刻
so in many ways I'm excited by this.
那么在很多方面我都为之兴奋
I've also of course would really like to see a competitor regardless
无论如何 我也很想看到一个竞争对手
because I think it's good and having more money for the space program is always fantastic
因为我认为这是好的 有更多的资金用于太空计划总是很美妙的
and I think it will make the hearings of Bill Nelson a little more spicy than we were expecting.
而我认为这会使(NASA局长)Bill Nelson的(提名)听证会比我们预计的更刺激
I'm Scott Manley. Fly Safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]